A Guide to the Records of the Charlottesville School Board 1869-2006
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Records of the Charlottesville School Board 1869-2006
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
14210
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Boxes 38-45 are restricted. Charlottesville City Schools staff may access with written permission of chair of the City School Board or the Superintendent of City Schools.
Acquisitions Information
The Charlottesville City School Board loaned the collection to the University of Virginia Library on December 20, 2007.
Biographical/Historical Information
One of the first public schools in Charlottesville dates back to [1881] and was named "Midway Grammar and High School" or Primary School, and was the school for white children. It was also referred to as Lane or Charlottesville School (although a high school was built in 1940 which was also named Lane after Principal James Walker Lane). Midway was located on the east end of Main Street and originally provided education for elementary, middle and high school students. There was a school for "Negroes" which was the "Jefferson Graded School" and was located in the Delevan Hotel building on 632 Main Street in 1865. It was later moved to Brown and Fifth Street Northwest [1926] near the western edge of the Vinegar Hill neighborhood. New schools were soon constructed, McGuffey Elementary in 1916 located on Second Street; Venable Elementary was built on Fourteenth Street in 1922; George Rogers Clark Elementary School was built in Belmont in 1930; and Lane High School was built on Preston Avenue and McIntire Road in 1940. These schools were built under the careful scrutiny of James G. Johnson, who was the Superintendent of Schools from1909 to 1946 and knew every detail of the construction. According to his correspondence, overseeing the construction on a weekly if not a daily basis caused him many sleepless nights and exhausted him physically and mentally.
Fendall R. Ellis was the next school superintendent from 1947 to 1964 and had the difficult task of trying to keep the schools open during desegregation. He was included in the lawsuits in all three of the important court cases in Charlottesville and worked closely with the attorney for the School Board, John S. Battle, Jr. Ellis tried to mediate between massive resisters and the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People in order to keep the schools open during desegregation.
As the number of school buildings multiplied and the issue of desegregation gained acceptance, the next school superintendents wrestled with more general issues in education, such as budgets, overcrowding, quality of education, new methods of teaching, the safety of students, busing, sex education in schools, and maintaining diversity in all of the Charlottesville City Schools. These school superintendents were George C. Tramontin from 1963 to 1966; Edward R. Rushton from 1967 to 1972; William J. Ellena from 1973 to 1981; Thomas J. McLernon from 1981 to 1982; Vincent C. Cibbarelli from 1982 to 1989; Joseph R. McGeehan from 1990 to 1995, and Dorothea Shannon [1996-2001].
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the official records of the Charlottesville School Board from 1869 to 2006, including information about events that occurred during the desegregation of the schools in Charlottesville, Virginia from 1954 to 1964. There is extensive correspondence, as well as legal documents, petitions from Oliver W. Hill to end segregation, an order from the Governor of Virginia to close the schools (1958 September), a report by Booker T. Reaves on the attitudes regarding desegregation, and transcripts of the major desegregation cases in Charlottesville: Doris Marie Allen et al., v. Fendall R. Ellis and the City of Charlottesville School Board, (1956 July 12), Caroline M. Dodson v. Fendall R. Ellis and the City of Charlottesville School Board, (1961 April 14), and Doris Dillard v. Fendall R. Ellis and the City of Charlottesville School Board, (1962 September 17).
Correspondents include Governor James Lindsay Almond, Jr., Governor Thomas B. Stanley, Superintendent of Schools Fendall R. Ellis, George C. Tramontin, John S. Battle, Jr., Oliver W. Hill, James Harry Michael, Jr., Thomas J. Michie, Booker T. Reaves, Charles E. Moran, Judge John Paul, and Sarah Patton Boyle. (Series I Desegregation correspondence and court cases)
There are also desegregation plans, news clippings, a report by Paul Gaston and Thomas Hammond, and speeches by John S. Battle, Jr., and Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr. (Series II General Desegregation)
The rest of the collection relates to general school issues facing the School Board and the City of Charlottesville. The superintendents of the schools worked closely with the City Council and their correspondence is represented in this collection. Correspondents include Bernard J. Haggerty, Lindsay Mount, Burkett Reynolds, G. A. Vogt, Mitchell Van Yahres, Francis H. Fife, Charles L. Barbour, Nancy O'Brien, Laurence A. Brunton, Frank L. Buck, Elizabeth "Bitsy" Waters, Alvin Edwards, Thomas J. Vandever, James E. Bowen, T. W. Edwards, Cole Hendrix, and David J. Toscano.
There is also correspondence between the superintendent of schools and legal counsel (James Harry Michael, Jr.) about general advice and legal updates for the School Board from 1923-1995. (Series III Correspondence)
There is detailed information about facilities management and the construction of Charlottesville schools including architectural drawings (from 1913-1940) in the correspondence of Superintendent of Schools, James G. Johnson and architects, Charles J. Calrow and Pendleton Scott Clark. The correspondence mentions that some of the Charlottesville contractors were upset that bids on the construction work was awarded to out of town businesses. (Series IV)
The schools mentioned in this collection are Midway Grammar and High (1895-?), Jefferson (1869-1958), McGuffey Elementary (1916-1973), Venable Elementary (1925-present), George Rogers Clark Elementary (1930-present), Lane High (1940-1973), Jackson P. Burley Middle (1949-present), Johnson Elementary (1954-present), Walker Upper Elementary (1966-present), Jackson-Via Elementary (1966-present), Burnley-Moran Elementary (1954-present), Greenbrier Elementary (1962-present), Buford Middle (1966-present), and Charlottesville High School (1974-present).
There are also School Board minutes from 1879, and 1896-1898 in a bound volume. (Series VI). Other minutes of the School Board are related to general topics and are filed with correspondence in Series I Desegregation correspondence, Series II General desegregation, Series III Correspondence and Series IV Facilities Management correspondence.
There is miscellaneous information about principals, schools, and teachers (including war bonds for teachers), financial information including bank statements, expenditures, and payroll information, news clippings, and photographs. There are also deeds, reports, and records with information about land purchases, annual reports, fire drills, lunch menus, census and enrollment records, and teacher record books with student grades and attendance records. There are also reel to reel tapes of School Board meetings, trophies, printing blocks, and a school banner. The collection contains approximately 16,500 items, 167 hollinger boxes, 6 cubic boxes and 76.5 linear feet.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into ten series and is mostly arranged in chronological order. Series I on Desegregation is divided into two subseries: A. Correspondence and B. Court cases. Series II is General desegregation, which includes plans, minutes, news clippings, information about organizations, reports, interview notes, speeches, and statements, all arranged by topic. Series III is Correspondence and has two subseries: A. Legal correspondence and B. Correspondence with City Council, and the correspondence of the school superintendents. Series IV is Facilities Management and has two subseries: A. Correspondence and B. Specifications. Series V is financial information. Series VI is minutes of the School Board from 1879 to 1898, Series VII contains news clippings, Series VIII is miscellaneous information about principals, teachers, and schools, Series IX is photographs, and Series X has deeds, reports, and records.
Box and Contents Listing
- Series I: Desegregation
  - A. Correspondence
    - Letter from Attorney General J. Lindsay Almond, Jr. to the Honorable Blake T. Newton, President, State Board of Education 1954 May 27, 1 item (Box-folder 1:1)
      Following the Court decision of Brown v. Board of Education, Attorney General Almond advised that the schools follow their current procedures regarding segregation until a final decree was made by the courts.
    - Letters from Dowell J. Howard, Superintendent of Public Instruction to the Superintendents of Virginia Schools 1954, June 7, July 6, 2 items (Box-folder 1:2)
      Mr. Howard requested that the Superintendents cooperate fully with Governor Thomas B. Stanley's order to operate the schools on the basis of segregation. Attached to his letter is census information for schools in Virginia in the 1950's.
    - Fendall R. Ellis sent Dr. F. G. Lankford Jr. a copy of a School Board Resolution regarding the recent Court decision 1954 October 27, 3 items (Box-folder 1:3)
      The School Board Resolution (which is included here) states that it will maintain the public school system, take cautions with the elimination of compulsory school attendance, stay flexible, and encourage people with different views to be able to work together. There is also an article from The Daily Progress about the Resolution and a letter from Dr. Ellis.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to the School Board members 1954 November 3, 1 item (Box-folder 1:4)
      Dr. Ellis wrote to the School Board regarding an article (that is not present) on "Segregation in the Schools" by John T. Fey, Dean of the Law School at George Washington University. James Harry Michael, Jr. recommended that each member read it.
    - Letters between Fendall R. Ellis and Mr. P.A. Wallenborn and an article from the Raleigh newspaper News and Observer1954 November 29, 3 items (Box-folder 1:5)
      Ellis thanked Wallenborn for sending him an article about a brief filed with the U. S. Supreme Court by the State of North Carolina and a desegregation plan. (The article is present.)
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to Dr. Lindley J. Stiles, Dean of the School of Education at the University of Virginia 1954 December 3, 2 items (Box-folder 1:6)
      Dr. Ellis thanked Dr. Stiles for writing to R. Stanley Goodman complimenting the Charlottesville City Board of Education on their resolution regarding the problem of segregation. The letter from Lindley J. Stiles to R. Stanley Goodman is included.
    - Correspondence between the public and Fendall R. Ellis against integration 1954-1958, 35 items (Box-folder 1:7)
      Comments include [they would be] "perfectly willing to abolish the present public school system" rather than "see mixed schools in Virginia;" "The negro is a pure jungle product;" "white children attend school during one part of the day and the Negro children attend during the other part of the day;" "Isenhower [sic] is a rabid integrationist, has entirely desegrated [sic] the armed forces of this nation." There are also news clippings about the abolishment of schools in Mississippi. Superintendent Ellis responded with a simple acknowledgement of their position.
    - Correspondence between the public and Fendall R. Ellis for integration 1956; 1958, 4 items (Box-folder 1:8)
      One letter is from a parent who supported integration and wanted to keep the schools open. Another is from parents who wanted their child to attend an integrated school and planned to send the child away to a more progressive school unless Charlottesville embraced integration in the schools. Dr. Ellis responded to each letter.
    - Letters from Fendall R. Ellis and Dowell J. Howard to the School Board and Division Superintendents 1955 June 14, 2 items (Box-folder 1:9)
      Ellis and Howard wrote to the School Board and Division Superintendents about the Supreme Court's opinion of May 31 which stated that "racial discrimination in public education is unconstitutional" but must be dealt with on a local level.
    - Letters from Fendall R. Ellis and Dowell J. Howard to the School Board 1955 June 28, 30, 2 items (Box-folder 1:10)
      The letters discuss the policy statement from the Governor which said that the decision of the United States Supreme Court created problems and would need appropriate legislation to support its views.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to R. Stanley Goodman, Jr. and a petition filed by the law firm of Hill, Martin and Robinson 1955 October 6, 2 items (Box-folder 1:11)
      Oliver W. Hill's petition requests that the School Board voluntarily desegregate the schools for the 1956-1957 school term.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to the School Board regarding an analysis of Brown v. Board by [James Harry] Michael 1955 November, 3 items (Box-folder 1:12)
      Dr. Ellis informed them of a meeting to discuss an analysis of Brown v. Board written by [James Harry] Michael. There is a list of questions from the Committee of the Whole and a copy of the analysis.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to the School Board and a telegram from the Pupil Placement Board 1956 January 3, 2 items (Box-folder 1:13)
      Ellis wrote to the School Board about a telegram from the placement board which ordered that the "local school boards and division superintendents are divested of all such powers" in the placement of pupils.
    - Correspondence between Fendall R. Ellis and James Harry Michael, Jr. about an article, "The Legal Liability of School Districts" (not present) 1956 March 1, 6, 2 items (Box-folder 1:14)
    - Letters between Oliver W. Hill and Fendall R. Ellis 1956 April 6, 5 items (Box-folder 1:15)
      Hill wrote that he was waiting for a response to his petition (see 1:11) Dr. Ellis responded that "no action has been taken in this matter…" Also included is a letter from Ellis to the School Board and an excerpt from the School Board minutes.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to Governor Thomas B. Stanley and a statement from Governor Stanley 1956 May 14, 2 items (Box-folder 1:16)
      Dr. Ellis wrote that the School Board would be meeting with Attorney General Almond concerning the law suit. Governor Stanley issued a statement announcing that he would request the Chairman of the Commission on Public Education to call the Executive Committee of the Commission into session.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to the Honorable John S. Battle, Jr.; copy of School Board Resolutions, and petition from Oliver W. Hill 1956 May 29, 3 items (Box-folder 1:17)
      Dr. Ellis wrote that he would send John Battle all of his correspondence with Oliver W. Hill. The petition has handwritten notes (possibly notes on the employment of the parents of the children in the petition.)
    - Letters from Fendall R. Ellis to James Harry Michael, Jr. and John S. Battle about a study on "Attitudes of Negroes in Charlottesville toward Segregated Schools" and a response from John S. Battle. A copy of the report (survey questionnaire and tabulated results, with commentary) is present. 1956 June 21, 3 items (Box-folder 1:18)
      The study (was prepared by Booker T. Reaves when he was a student in Professor Lambert Molyneaux's class on Race Relations in the Department of Sociology at the University of Virginia.)
    - Letters from Fendall R. Ellis to the School Board, The Daily Progress and Dr. Thomas T. Hamilton concerning the Civil Action Case against Dr. Ellis in the Federal District Court 1956 June-July, 6 items (Box-folder 1:19)
      Dr. Ellis sent a copy of the Summons to the editor of The Daily Progress, and letters to the School Board about meeting with John S. Battle to prepare an answer to the case. The Summons is included (June 1, 1956).
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to members of the School Board concerning an informal meeting of the Board 1956 July 7, 1 item (Box-folder 1:20)
      Dr. Ellis proposed that they meet to discuss the Civil Action Case which was scheduled to go to the Federal District Court on July 12 th.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to Attorney General James Lindsay Almond, Jr. and a statement on the meaning of "deliberate speed." (see also 4:9) 1956 July 7, 2 items (Box-folder 1:21)
    - Letter from Charles "Chic" E. Moran, Jr. to Fendall R. Ellis in support of desegregation 1956 August 20, 1 item (Box-folder 1:22)
      Charles "Chic" E. Moran offered the services of the Virginia Council on Human Relations to bring in consultants to help the city successfully meet the problems of integration.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to Principals regarding the Civil Action Case 1956 August 29, 1 item (Box-folder 1:23)
      Dr. Ellis gave instructions to all teachers and school personnel to refrain from commenting about the lawsuit and the "serious problem confronting us."
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to Vincent Shea, Comptroller, University of Virginia 1956 November 26, 1 item (Box-folder 1:24)
      Dr. Ellis asked Vincent Shea if the City of Charlottesville was eligible for any federal funds for elementary and secondary education.
    - Letters between Fendall R. Ellis and Dean F. D. G. Ribble, Law School, University of Virginia 1956 November 26, 2 items (Box-folder 1:25)
      Dr. Ellis sent Dean Ribble a brief statement that Ellis had prepared on his interpretations of "Meaning and Implications of 'Deliberate Speed." Ellis suggested that desegregation begin with one grade a year.
    - Letters from John S. Battle, Jr. regarding his legal fees during the end of segregation 1957; 1960-1963; 1966, 17 items (Box-folder 1:26)
      Superintendent Ellis wrote in one of his letters, "Judge Paul's favorable decision is a source of great encouragement to us all." (August 26, 1960)
    - Letter from James Harry Michael, Jr. to the Charlottesville School Board, an article about Virginia integration, and the Fourth Circuit Court ruling 1957 January 1, 9, 3 items (Box-folder 1:27)
      The article, "Order to Integrate In Virginia Upheld" from the Little Rock Arkansas Gazette, suggested that the state did not have to follow the Supreme Court ruling of May 17, 1954. There is also a letter from Fendall R. Ellis to the School Board members with the text of the Fourth Circuit Court's ruling that they must put an end to segregation in the schools.
    - Letter from Attorney General James Lindsay Almond, Jr. and Mark R. Hawes about the NAACP to Virginia Superintendents of Schools 1957 March 1, 2 items (Box-folder 1:28)
      Attorney General James Lindsay Almond Jr. requested school officials to send any information regarding petitions filed by the NAACP to Mark R. Hawes, the Chief Counsel of the Florida Legislative Investigation Committee, who was investigating the NAACP.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to Attorney General James Lindsay Almond, Jr. and an excerpt of the School Board minutes 1957 March 14, 2 items (Box-folder 1:29)
      Superintendent Ellis sent Attorney General James Lindsay Almond, Jr. a resolution to retain the Honorable John S. Battle, Jr. to serve as their counsel and to also request the legal services of the Office of the Attorney General.
    - Letters between Fendall R. Ellis and John S. Battle, Jr. regarding a meeting with Judge John Paul 1957 July 20, 2 items (Box-folder 1:30)
      Dr. Ellis asked if they could postpone the meeting.
    - Letter from Booker Reaves to Fendall R. Ellis about the bond election 1957 July 17, 1 item (Box-folder 1:31)
      Attached are lists of Jefferson School Patrons who helped with the School Bond Election
    - Letter from Ben D. Lacy to Fendall R. Ellis and a senate report, "The Doctrine of Interposition Its History and Application" 1957 July 29, 2 items (Box-folder 1:32)
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to School Board members with copies of Judge Paul's order and the action of the Pupil Placement Board 1957 August 8, 2 items (Box-folder 1:33)
      Judge Paul ruled that no children would be denied entrance to a school because a parent failed to apply for a pupil assignment with the pupil placement board. He also ruled that the pupil placement board would act only as a guide for school officials and would not be an enforcement agency. There is also a press release statement about the decree.
    - Letter from Dr. Robert D. Wright, to Dr. R. W. Garnett, President of Lane High School Parent Teachers Association 1957 November 8, 1 item (Box-folder 1:34)
      Dr. Wright, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare cited the violence in Little Rock, Arkansas as an example of what could happen if there was no leadership in following the laws.
    - Letters of praise for Fendall R. Ellis 1958 May and September, 2 items (Box-folder 1:35)
      Correspondents include Senator Theodore "Ted" Roosevelt Dalton and the Venable Faculty Committee.
    - Letter from Oliver W. Hill with a petition to Fendall R. Ellis and the School Board 1958 May 18, 1 item (Box-folder 1:36)
      The petition requests admittance for certain students in the public schools of the city by September 1958 without regard to their race or color.
    - Letters from Fendall R. Ellis to the School Board 1958 May 21, June 4, and September 3, October 17, 4 items (Box-folder 1:37)
      Superintendent Ellis informed them of special meetings with John S. Battle, Jr.
    - Letter from the secretary of the Venable Parent Teachers Association to R. Stanley Goodman, Jr., Chairman of the School Board 1958 June 11, 1 item (Box-folder 1:38)
      Dorothy Owen sent the results of a poll from the parents of Venable School pupils to the School Board. One hundred and seventy seven parents wanted some measure of integration and one hundred and twenty eight preferred that Venable School be closed.
    - Letters requesting the names of the parents of Venable School pupils 1958 June 24, 4 items (Box-folder 1:39)
      Mr. and Mrs James P. Williams, Mr. and Mrs. J. F. Dulaney, Mr. and Mrs. R. G. Faulconer, and Mrs. Harold M. Burrows requested a list of the names and addresses of the parents of Venable School pupils for the use of a poll [inquiring about desegregation and the closing of Venable School.
    - Letters between Fendall R. Ellis and Oliver W. Hill and the School Board Resolution (desegregation plan or "Battle Plan") 1958 July 21, 22, 2 items (Box-folder 1:40)
      Mr. Hill requested a copy of the resolution (which is present) that designated six geographic areas for school districts and interviews and testing.
    - Letter from J. R. Jarman, Lane High School Parent Teachers Association to Mrs. Morris Brown recommending against sending a poll 1958 July 23, 1 item (Box-folder 1:41)
      Mr. Jarman, president of the Lane PTA wrote that it would be better if they did not send a questionnaire "at this time."
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to the Honorable William R. Hill 1958 July 24, 1 item (Box-folder 1:42)
      Superintendent Ellis congratulated Hill on his statement to the press regarding the school situation.
    - Letters from Oliver W. Hill to Fendall R. Ellis requesting admission to schools on behalf of his clients 1958 July 25, 31, 2 items (Box-folder 1:43)
      Hill requested that Carol Williams and Sylvia Delorus Morton be admitted to public schools regardless of their race or color. He also wrote Ellis that they were studying the validity of the "Battle Plan" and had advised their clients not to appear for personal interviews.